In this chapter, we will
learn about exceptions, also known as `
try` statements. Specifically,
in this video, we will
learn about the legendary statement
called `try and cash`. The word "try" means "to try," and "
cash"
means "to catch" or "to catch an
error." More specifically,
you can read the documentation for this video at
this link. It's written in detail.
First, let's look
at a problem. You
see, normally
we allow the user to input any character.
For example, we let the user perform a
division calculation, 10 divided by x, where x is
entered from the keyboard. When
we let the user input characters from the
keyboard, many cases can
occur. The perfect case is when the
user enters a valid input. But there
are also many cases where the user
enters the number 0. 10 cannot be divided by
0, or the user...  If we use
alphanumeric input, for example,
our program
will definitely crash. Now,
we want to know how to make it so that every time an invalid character is
entered, the
program will display an error message saying, "
You entered an
invalid character. Please try again." That way,
our program won't
crash,
and we'll display
that message until the user enters
a valid character. To be
more specific, I'll write
this program very quickly. We
have video 52, called chapter
9. I'll create chapter 9.
Inside this, I'll create
a new package called
Tab ch 9, then we'll add a
video and a
class. It's
very easy.
Inside this, you'll add a
main function and...  Here, I'll copy
the scanner function, guys. Let
me have this scanner again.
First, I'll
give it something like integer,
integer x. Actually,
why is our scanner
giving an error? Ah, here it is. You'll
give it something like `in x`. That's exactly what the scanner says. Now
you can
input x from the keyboard. At the same time,
I'll print it out. System m, system m,
one, system m, what? The result, the
result, the
result. 10 divided by x, 10 divided by x equals this.
You'll give me a calculation, this
is 10 divided by x, with x
we ​​input from the keyboard. A
very simple program. And
now I'll run it. You'll see...
Ah, here I'll give it another line, system
out, right here. We'll put it
at the beginning of the function: system out,
system out, input X, input
x,
input x equals this. Please delete
the ln part. We will...  In
this Java application, you always
input X on the same line. For example, if you input
2, and press Enter, the result is
10 divided by X equals 5.
This is the perfect case,
but let's run it again.
Let's run it again. If you input X
equals 0, for example, if you input 0, the
program
will immediately show a red error.
It says "exception,"
which is what we'll be learning
today. It says "exception," and then it divides by 0,
and our program crashes. At this point,
our program is finished. It wo
n't run, right? So, the
first thing I want to
clarify is what an exception is. In
reality, if
you translate the English word "exception" into
Vietnamese, it means "exception."
However, during the
coding process, you never say
where the "exception" is. We'll just talk about
the word "exception." This is
one of the keywords that...  You're
practically using it all the time, just like when
you say "go
for coffee twice," "
coffee twice," that's it. You never
translate it as "there's coffee at the top of a mountain,"
you never
translate the meaning, right? So
here, our program, when run, has
two steps. The
first step is code compilation.
Code compilation
converts our Java code into B-code.
This B-code is for the Java Virtual
Machine to run. Note that
during this compilation process,
if there's an error, it immediately reports it.
The second step
is
running the source code, right? If
there's an error, our program
will crash. Note that
exceptions only
occur when we
run the program.
Here, it's like
our program has already
run.
Our program is running. I enter
a character like this, press Enter, and
it crashes. So, this
is an exception, right? The
first concept I
want you to understand is that exceptions
occur during the
program's execution, right?
Regarding the classification of
exceptions, I have
a link here. I
think that if you want to
learn from A to Z, meaning you want to
learn mechanically, you
can classify exceptions into categories: those
we define, and those
already
built into Java. Exceptions are
further divided into two types: checked
exceptions and unchecked exceptions. However,
personally, I don't
recommend learning mechanically like
this. If you want to learn mechanically
like this, please refer to
the link I've provided at the beginning.
This link is from
Oracle.  Look on the
left side here;
you can read everything about exceptions here.
It's extremely detailed, so
if you have time, I recommend
you use it as a reference. However,
within the scope of this course,
I'll skip the concept of
exception classification. We'll
simply understand that
our program has an error. How to
handle that error
is the concept I want to
share with you here. In reality, an
exception is how we
handle predictable exceptions. This is how
we'll learn
in this course.
To do that, we call it "checking" (checking the ID, checking the exception). There
's a very simple way: the try
and cash syntax.
First, we'll use the `
try` statement. `try` means we'll try to
run the code, and `cash`
means that if an error occurs, we
'll execute the `cash` statement.  Here's an example. Look,
for example, inside this, we're using something
called "Avoiding
errors." Now, I'll add
a try-and-catch loop. You
just need to type "try," "control," and a
space, and it will suggest code for you.
For now, don't
worry about what the exception is;
let's just make the code run,
right? I'll paste it here.
This time, look. In the case where
I enter "size," for example, I'll
print something like this. I'll give it a "
system out run error." Pay
attention to this. Distinguish this: if
we don't have the try-
and-catch part,
our log will look bad like this, and
our program will crash.
This time, I've added
the try-and-catch, and when you run it again,
you'll see the difference. I
enter X = 0. Look, it doesn't
print those red error messages anymore.  But
now, it only prints a log line
like this. Later, what
we do here, in
case of an error, we will use `do
something` instead of letting
our program run.
This is the meaning of the
try-catch block. To be
more specific, I will modify the example
we call division by zero. I want
us to input until
it says "OK," then we stop
inputting. To do that,
I will modify it. You will
give us an infinite loop `wi`. We will
give us a `
white true` loop like this. We will give
us a try-catch block.
In reality,
we have this: If we
still input incorrectly (regarding the
White part), in case
of an error, we will give it
a `
run error with x`. We will print
out `x`.  The fact is,
I'm going to throw that 'x'
out. Okay guys, this time,
in case it has an error, what do you do? Well,
here we'll call it an error,
you don't need to do anything.
Because this is an infinite loop.
In case it fails here,
it will run into this 'cas' line,
this 'cas' line will run, then it will
repeat this 'White Shu' loop,
and finally, if you can run
to this point, I'll break it.
If you can run the '
system out' line
without errors, then we'll exit
the loop.
This time, I'll run it again. You'll see,
I'll run it again. I'll enter 'X'. For
example, if I enter '0',
it will say 'run error with x =
0', right? Okay, we'll give it
this line. I'll cut down to this 'd' line.  Let's
run it again, guys.
This line says "input X," for example,
this time we'll set it to 0. It
says "run error with x = 0." We
'll go back and input X again. We'll go
back and input X again. Let's input a BC x yz, for
example. So, for
this one, we've got an error. Okay, let's
cut it down here.
No, we throw it
down here.
If we do it like that...
Why isn't it the second time we get an error? What is it? Ah,
so...
this is another exception.
Another exception of ours is here.
We've
got an error because we're
inputting an integer. So, for
this X, there is... It seems like... yes,
we'll declare a
variable. It's like this... yes, we only
handle the zero...
It gets an exception right here, it's quite
strange. Let's handle this...
To try and handle
this, we'll use a
second technique: multiple try
and catch loops. You can nest them.
For example, here we'll use them in
parallel. We'll try
and catch
this X, and we'll also try X
in case an error occurs.
If an error happens, we'll break it.
We'll break it, and then... oh wait,
we'll continue. Sorry, guys...
continue... continue... Why do we
continue? Because when there's an error, when
we enter x incorrectly, we'll
exit and run the
X input loop again. Because if you run it
down here, it won't solve the
problem, right? So right
here, we'll cut this...
run error with X. This time, pay
attention. I'll copy and paste it
down here. Just run error with x.
And please delete
this line. Please delete the
line below because we do
n't have that X.  X, however, if
we do it this way, you will
directly enter this for me. Enter X,
then you will try and cat here.
Try and cat are nested, you know.
This time, let's try
again. You can see that it's a
little complicated. Okay, delete this and
then try again. You try again. Okay,
enter x. For example, here I still enter
the number 0. Enter X, and it still
prints this because in case there
is an error,
we can't print x. It's
quite frustrating. I will continue entering
here. After a while of fixing the
error, I finally fixed
our error. It's quite
frustrating because, to be honest with
you, when I work, it's very rare that I
go back to the beginning like
this. In fact, for the
scanner function, I went to
Google and searched.
Quickly, I searched and...  I'm using
Java's try-catch block with the scanner,
similar to the previous time.
For
this scanner, you need to use the `
scanner` function like this to
stop it.
Otherwise, we'll get an infinite loop.
So, here, I'll reopen
our code block and run it again for
you to see. For example, if
I enter X as 0, and then enter x =
0, the code
is correct, but we have an error,
right? I'll give it a `
run error`. I'll give it a `
run error`.
I'll print out X.
This time, I'll run it again for
you to see. If we enter x = 0, and
we run x = 0, right? It gives an error,
meaning it goes into the CAS block. And
in the case where
we enter X randomly like
this, it will go into the `run
error` block.  Okay guys, you'll see
this: I press Enter, and it
runs into the Run R command, and we've
returned to the value of X. For example, if I
enter x = 5, the result is
2.
This is how you can
handle our error. This is
our exception. Why do
we have this keyword 'exception'?
At this point, we have
n't used the keyword 'a' yet. In the
next videos, I will
guide you on how to understand
this exception in more detail, and
we will also learn
about the keyword 'finally'. See
you in the next videos!